A Guide to the VCU Special Collections and Archives Subject Files M 561
James Branch Cabell Library
VCU Special Collections and Archives Subject Files
1970-2010
1930-2010, undated
James Branch Cabell Library
Virginia Commonwealth University. University Library Services. Special Collections and Archives
M 561
3 Linear Feet
Access restrictions
The collection is open for research
Content Description
This is an artificial collection that consists of subject files maintained by VCU Special Collections and Archives of mostly 20th century printed materials related to Richmond collected by the department over the course of four decades. Many of the subject files compliment materials in the Special Collections and Archives holdings.
The collection is composed of folders containing newspaper and magazine clippings, promotional materials, brochures, published reports, correspondence, and a variety of ephemera on subjects ranging from historic buildings and city businesses to numerous organizations and civic groups. Many of the topics are related to the cultural life of the city and its history. Nearly 140 topics are included. Most of the materials date from the late 20th century. A significant portion of the collection are VCU undergraduate student reports produced in the early 1990s documenting the architectural history of buildings including many residences in the area surrounding the university.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by file title.
Acquisition Information
This collection has been created by the staff of Special Collections and Archives.
- 1000 W. Franklin St., 1993
- 1006 W. Franklin St., 1991
- 1013 W. Franklin St., 1994
- 1015 W. Franklin St., 1991
- 1101 W. Franklin St., 1993
- 1218 W. Franklin St., 1992
- 1501 Grove Ave. [Designer House in the Fan, 1976], 1975-1976
- 1616 Monument Ave., 1994
- 1626 Monument Ave., 1994
- 1708 Gallery, undated, 1980s-2000s
- 2000 Monument Ave., 1994
- 2200 Monument Ave., 1994
- 2304 Monument Ave., 1994
- 900 block of W. Franklin St. [listing of indviduals who lived in specific houses on this block], 1994
- 926 W. Franklin St., 1991
- 932 W. Franklin St., 1994
- 6th Street Marketplace, undated, 1980s
- Agecroft Hall, 2000
- Ambassodor Apartments, 1108 W. Franklin St., 1993
- Authors, 1920s-2000s
- Bank of Virginia building, 800 E. Main St., 1992
- Battlefields, 1930s
- Black History Museum, 1980s-2000s
- Blues Armory, 6th and Marshall St, 1980s
- Branch House, 2501 Monument Ave, 1992
- Carillon, Byrd Park, 1932
- Carpenter Theater at the Dominion Energy Center, 600 E. Grace St., 1983, 1992
- Central National Bank building, 219 E. Broad St., 1977
- Central Richmond Association, 1980s
- Chesterfield Apartment building, 900 W. Franklin St., 1991
- Chesterman Place, 100 - 102 W. Franklin St., 1992, 1994
- Church Hill, undated, 1990, 1999-2002
- Churches, undated, 1970s-2000s
- City of Richmond Annual Reports, 1974-1975, 1980s-2000s
- Civil War commemoration, undated, 1917, 1930, 1954 1959, 1960s
- Collegiate Schools, 1970s-1980s
- Columbia building, 1301-1307 E. Cary St., 1993
- Crozet House, 100 E. Main St., 1993
- Debutantes Ball, 1963, 1966, 1969, 1971-1975
- Dooley Madison building, 212 W. Franklin St., undated
- Ellen Glasgow House, 1 W. Main St., 1993
- Elmira Shelton House, 2407 E. Grace St., 1992
- Emergency Shelter, 1993-1994
- Ethyl Corporation building, 300 S. 4th St., 1992
- Family and Children's Service of Richmond, 1970s
- Fan District, 1980s-1990s
- Federated Arts Council of Richmond, 1982
- First English Lutheran Church, 1992
- Franklin Street Entrances, 1995
- Franklin Street Inlaid Wood Floors, 1995
- Franklin Street Interiors, 1995
- Franklin Street Mantels, 1995
- Frankln Street Staircases, 1995
- Grace and Holy Trinity Church, 2000
- Grace House, 1969
- Greater Richmond Transit Company (GRTC), undated
- Gresham Court apartment building, 1030 W. Franklin St., 1991
- Greyston Apartments, 1012 W. Franklin St., 1991
- Guide Books, undated, 1950s-1980s
- Historic Richmond Foundation, undated, 1979, 1980s, 1991, 1992
- Home for Needy Confederate Women, 301 N. Sheppard St., 1993
- Ions, Willoughby, 1970s check
- Jackson Ward, undated, 1978, 1982, 1990, 2000
- Jacob House, 610 W. Cary St., 1990s
- James River Film Festival, 2004, 2013, 2015
- Jamgochian, Hugh (architect), 1962-1963
- Jewish Community, undated, 1990s-2000s
- John Marshall House, 818 E. Marshall St., 1992
- John Miller House, 617 S. Cherry St., 1996
- June Jubilee, 1986-1987
- Junior League of Richmond, 1963, 1973, 1983, 2000
- Lewis Ginter Botanical Garden, 2000-2006
- Linden Row, 100 E. Franklin St., 1993
- Maggie Walker House, 110 1/2 E. Leigh St., 2000
- Main Street Station, 1990s
- Maps and guide books, undated, 1940s--1990s
- Maymont Park and Foundation, 1980s-2000s
- Metropolitan Richmond Chamber of Commerce, 1980s-1990s
- Metropolitan Richmond Convention Center and Visitors Bureau, 1980s-1990s
- Monroe Park, undated, 1900--1990s
- Monument Avenue, 1990
- Mosque building, 6 N. Laurel St., undated, 1927, 1990s
- Museum of the Confederacy, undated, 1918, 1960s, 1980s
- Musical Programs, undated, 1918, 1923
- Old City Hall, undated, 1993
- Oregon Hill, undated, 1989
- Pleasants Hardware, 1976, 1994
- Powhatan Courthouse, Old Buckingham Rd., Powhattan, VA, 1992
- Richmond Area Community Center, 1992
- Richmond Art Company building, 101 E. Grace St., 1992
- Richmond City Chronology, 1997
- Richmond City Council, 1970s, 1990s
- Richmond City Music Association, undated, 1930, 1940s--1950s
- Richmond Community Action Program (R-CAP), 1980s
- Richmond Forum, 1980s--2000s
- Richmond International Airport, 1980s--1990s
- Richmond Jazz Society, 1990s
- Richmond Metropolitan Blood Service, 1975
- Richmond Opera Group, Inc., undated, 1940s--1950s
- Richmond Public Library, 1970s--1980s
- Richmond Public Schools, undated, bulk 1920s -- 1970s
- Richmond Redevelopment and Housing Authority, 1975
- Richmond Regional Drug Information, Richmond City Health Department, 1972
- Richmond Regional Planning, 1971, 1980s
- Richmond Symphony Orchestra, 1935-1936
- Richmond Symphony, 1950s--1960s, 1980s
- ROSMY (Richmond Organization for Sexual Minority Youth), undated, 1990s--2000s
- Samuel Pleasants Parsons House, 601 Spring St., 1990s
- Second Baptist Church building, Adams and Franklin Streets, 1992
- Second Presbyterian Church, undated, 1993
- St. James Church, 1205 W. Franklin St., 1968, 1992
- St. Paul's Episcopal Church, 1980s, 1992
- Stuart Court Apartments, 1600 Monument Ave., 1992
- The James, 1972
- The Warsaw building, 1401 Floyd Ave, undated
- Tobacco companies, undated, 1960, 1995
- Tobacco Company Restaurant building, 1201 E. Cary St., 1992
- Transportation (including trolleys and streetcars), 1940s, 1990
- Tusca Villas Apartments, 507-509 N. Boulevard Ave., 1992
- Union Station (Science Museum), 1992
- Union Theological Society, 1940s--1950s
- University of Richmond, undated, 1920s--1960s
- Virginia Holocaust Museum, 1998--2000s
- Virginia Trust Company building, 823 E. Main St., 1993
- Visual Arts Center of Richmond, 1980s--2000s
- Watts Hall, Union Theological Seminary, 3401 Brook Rd., 1993
- White House of the Confederacy, 1201 E. Clay St., undated, 1992
- Winston House, 103 E. Grace St., 1992